William Clement Bryant Papers
Buffalo History Museum. Research Library
William Clement Bryant Papers
1778 - 1898
Personal and professional papers of William Clement Bryan, an attorney who came to work in Buffalo in 1854.
3 boxes
Bryant, Wm. Clement (William Clement)
The Buffalo History Museum 1 Museum Court Buffalo, NY 14216 Phone: 716-873-9644 ext. 306 Fax: 716-873-8754 Email: library@buffalohistory.org URI: http://www.buffalohistory.org
Researchers wishing to access this collection must apply for a Scholar Pass and present valid photo ID upon arrival to the library.
Born in Orleans County in 1830, Bryant read law with Judge Selden in Clarkson, then came to Buffalo in 1854, practicing with William H. Greene from 1867 to 1872, when he became the attorney for the Western Savings Bank. He studied the history and traditions of the North American Indians and originated the movement to erect a monument over the grave of Red Jacket. He served as president of the Buffalo Historical Society in 1876 and as president of the Thomas Orphan Asylum for many years. He also founded the Archaeological Club of the Buffalo Society of Natural Sciences. He died on Sept. 3, 1898.
Red Jacket, Seneca chief, approximately 1756-1830; Lay, John H; Parish, Jasper, 1767-1836; Wilkeson, Samuel, 1781-1848; Gilbert family; Thayer Brothers; Beaver (Ship).; Indians of North America -- Games.; Iroquois Indians.; Seneca Indians; Society of Friends; treaties; wills; Allen, Orlando, 1803-1874; Bidwell, Daniel D. (Daniel Davidson), 1819-1864; Conover, George S. (George Stillwell), 1824-; Hyde, Jabez B. (Jabez Backus), 1774-1855; Jones, Horatio, 1763-1836; Letchworth, William Pryor, 1823-1910; Lossing, Benson John, 1813-1891; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895; Pierce, M. B. (Maris Bryant), 1811-1874; Scattergood, Joseph; Spaulding, Rufus.; Strong, Nathaniel T., -1872.; Wilgus, Nathaniel, 1793-1873; Wilson, Peter, Seneca chief, -1872.; Wright, Asher, 1803-1875; Wright, Laura M. (Laura Maria), 1809-1886; Bible Society of Erie County (N.Y.).
Letters received from Orlando Allen, Daniel D. Bidwell, William P. Letchworth and others, mostly regarding Bryant’s historical research, especially into Seneca Indian history and traditions, 1854—1889; correspondence and other papers of Asher Wright, 1820—1888, including letters from Joseph Scattergood of Philadelphia and other members of the Society of Friends regarding the Seneca Nation, from Peter Wilson, a Seneca chief and physician, and letters by Wright to the Seneca and to various church bodies; a treaty and a treaty amendment involving New York State and the Seneca, 1830 and 1837; Seneca, Cayuga and Onondaga Nations accounts, letters, power of attorney, petitions and statements to government officials, 1831—1839 and undated; a copy of Laura M. Wright’s will, 1886; an affidavit concerning the torpedo invented by John H. Lay during the Civil War, 1867; addresses, reminiscences and papers presented ‘to the Buffalo Historical Society on Native Americans and on the early settlers and history of Buffalo and surrounding area, ca. 1833—1872; and a minute book of the Bible Society of Erie County, 1829—1834.
- Correspondence, 1778 - 1889; I
  - William Clement Bryant, 1854 - 1889; A
    - Letters received, 1857 - 1888 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letterbook, 1854 - 1892; This volume underwent conservation treatment in 2013 by Halaina Demba, a student in the Art Conservation Department at Buffalo State College. (Box 1)
  - Asher Wright, 1778 - 1888; B
    - Letters received and other papers, 1778 - 1875; Includes some letters received by others, including Maris Pierce, William Pryor Letchworth, and Laura M Wright. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Letterbook, 1820 - 1898; Includes letters received by William Clement Bryant and others. This volume underwent conservation treatment in 2013 by Halaina Demba, a student in the Art Conservation Department at Buffalo State College. (Box 1)
- Treaties, 1830 - 1897; II
  - Treaties, 1830 - 1837; 1 treaty signed on 6 March 1830, altering and amending a treaty from 12 Sept. 1815, regarding annual payment to Seneca. This 3 page copy was transcribed on 6 August 1841 from an original in “the Secretary’s Office, State of New York.” 1 agreement, 1 page, between Heman Potter and George Lindsey, Seneca chief, regarding future payment for lands vacated by Seneca if they agree to move west of the Mississippi, 1837 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Seneca, Cayuga and Onondaga Nations, 1831 - 1839; III
  - Accounts, letters and statements to government officials, power of attorney and petitions, 1831 - 1839 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Affidavit and will, 1867 - 1886; IV
  - Affidavit and Will, 1867 - 1886; Affidavit of William B. Cushing regarding John L. Lay’s invention of a torpedo and torpedo apparatus used to destroy the Rebel Ram Albemarl, 10 July 1867; will of Laura M. Wright, 19 Feb. 1886 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Historical research, addresses and writings, ca. 1833-1872; V
  - Native Americans, A
    - Paper read before the Buffalo Historical Society on annuities paid to members of the Six Nations tribes (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Seneca history and traditions (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Seneca history and traditions (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Red Jacket (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Fish Carrier, Ramrod, Steeprock, Mary Jemison and others (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Wampum, Indian games (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Origin of Indian names (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Notes by George S. Conover on Old Smoke or Old Ring, and Young Smoke or Young Ring (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Copies from the Canadian Archives (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Reminiscence, 1866 - 1872; B
    - Rufus Spaulding, 1866 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Nathaniel Wilgus on the Three Thayers, 1869 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Orlando Allen (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - E.G. Spaulding and William Hodge on Samuel Wilkeson, 1872 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Horatio Jones, related to Orlando Allen (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Biographies, ca. 1833; C
    - Biographies, 1833; Jasper Parish, by Stephen Parish from his father’s notes, ca. 1833; Sir John Johnson, undated; narrative of the Gilbert family, captured by Iroquois, undated
  - Miscellaneous, D
    - Papers on Buffalo Harbor, Genesee River and the sloop Beaver, wrecked on her voyage from Fort Schlosser to Detroit on 8 Aug. 1763 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Notes and miscellaneous pages (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Bible Society of Erie County, 1829 - 1834; VI
  - Minutes, 1829 - 1834 (Box 3, Folder 9)